Finding Aid for Sigma Nu. Gamma Nu Chapter (University of Michigan) records, 1902-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sigma Nu. Gamma Nu Chapter (University of Michigan) records 1902-1981
Sigma Nu. Gamma Nu Chapter (University of Michigan).
2.5 linear feet.
9941 Bimu F47 2
University of Michigan chapter of Greek letter fraternity. Meeting minutes and financial records, pledging and initiation records, alumni records, visual materials and miscellaneous.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Gamma Nu chapter of Sigma Nu Fraternity (donor no. 8711 ) in April 1998.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Sigma Nu fraternity was founded in 1869 at the Virginia Military Institute (VMI) in response to the strict hazing and obedience policies adhered to at the university. The founders, James Frank Hopkins, Greenfield Quarles, and James McIlvane Riley, wanted to create a different kind of brotherhood than already found at VMI. They replaced hazing and fear with fellowship and equality among all members. This ideal has since evolved into one of the largest Greek letter fraternities in the nation, as of 1998. With more than 100 chapters distributed around the United States, the organization continues to grow and initiate new members each year.
The Gamma Nu chapter of Sigma Nu was founded at the University of Michigan on September 29, 1902. The focus of the chapter ranged from internal events, such as social functions, to external participation in student government and other campus-wide activities. Members were primarily concerned with the state of the chapter, but still formed committees to deal with university policies and events. A political committee was formed to understand, comment, and establish policy on both the university and national governments.
The chapter was originally located in a red brick building with a spire at 915 Oakland Street. As the chapter and its needs grew in 1919, money was actively collected to fund a new residence. On August 16, 1919, Frederick Day and Jim Bailey signed the mortgage that installed the chapter at its present location, 700 Oxford Street. This home once belonged to the Dean of the School of Music and was a music conservatory.
In the 1940s and 1950s, the chapter began policies and procedures on linking current members with alumni. As a result of this drive to contact and maintain their historical roots, lists of initiates and alumni were created and updated, composite pictures were preserved, and copies of the national Sigma Nu magazine, The Delta, were put on file in the house. In 1941, an effort to gather information on all living alumni resulted in records filed away in the chapter's library.
While the 1960s and 1970s brought a large scale renovation to the chapter house, there was a decline in overall membership. Initiate records and composite photographs reflect this drop-off in membership and a higher percentage of members had to take office. This resulted in more commitments and higher personal responsibility to the chapter.
Sigma Nu records have been divided into the following series: Meeting Minutes and Financial Records, Pledging and Initiation Records, Alumni Records, Visual Materials, and Miscellaneous. These materials describe the history of the Gamma Nu chapter of Sigma Nu at the University of Michigan, and the national fraternity as well.
Subjects:
Sigma Nu. Gamma Nu chapter (University of Michigan); Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Sigma Nu. Gamma Nu chapter (University of Michigan); Fraternities and sororities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Meeting Minutes and Financial Records
  The series comprised of Meeting Minutes and Financial Records contain the records of the first chapter of Sigma Nu at the University of Michigan, as well as the meeting minutes from the first seventeen years. These books detail motions requiring approval, whether they were carried or not, appointment to positions, the installation of officers, reactions to petitions and financial dealings.
  - Record of Chapter Minutes, September 29, 1902-October 20, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Records of Payments for Brothers, 1915-1925 (Box 1)
  - House Expenses, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - House Budget, 1975 (Box 1)
  - House Mortgage, August 16, 1919 (Box 1)
- Pledging and Initiation Records
  Pledging and Initiation Records date from 1905 to 1980, yet are not a complete record of all who pledged or were initiated into the Gamma Nu chapter. The information in these documents includes name, high school attended, hometown, parents' names, department entered in school, year entered in school, expected date of graduation, and date initiated into the fraternity. This demographic data reflects the differing backgrounds and education of the men entering Sigma Nu in these years.
  - Pledging Records, 1959-1971, 1975-1984, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Pledge Education Manuals, 1946, 1964, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Initiation Records, 1905-1913, 1918-1929, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Initiation Records, 1929-1947, 1959-1985, 10 folders (Box 2)
- Alumni Records
  Alumni Records are comprised of a complete listing of all Gamma Nus initiated from member numbers 1 through 1271, along with their last known address. Deceased members are denoted, as well as members whose whereabouts are unknown. A listing from 1902 to 1941 is present, consisting of the year graduated, personal information, involvement while on campus, occupation, marital status, and children. This provides information on what Gamma Nu alumni have accomplished during and after their time at Michigan, along with where they live and the type of lifestyle they might lead.
  - Gamma Nu (University of Michigan Chapter) Alumni, 1902-1941 (Box 2)
    (in metal file box)
  - Alumni A-D, 1902-1941 (Box 3)
  - Alumni E-H, 1902-1941 (Box 3)
  - Alumni I-L, 1902-1941 (Box 3)
  - Alumni M-P, 1902-1941 (Box 3)
  - Alumni Q-Z, 1902-1941 (Box 3)
  - Listing of Gamma Nus (University of Michigan Chapter), 1902-1985 (Box 3)
  - Listing of Missing Gamma Nus (University of Michigan Chapter), 1905-1978 (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials series contains slides and photographs of the members of the fraternity engaged in activities ranging from social and campus events to community service, spanning from around 1914 to the 1980s.
  - Photographs, 1914-1980s, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Slides, 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous Records series consists of general fraternity information. This includes sheet music to songs no longer sung by the Gamma Nu chapter. The chapter has no other copies of these songs. A note from a Mrs. Cheffy, who presented the chapter with the sheet music, is part of this series, as she presented the sheet music to the chapter. Also within this series are letters from the national fraternity and an essay from the Epsilon Theta chapter at MIT on the issue of whether to let women into the national fraternity. A humorous spin-off of the national fraternity magazine is preserved, written in the 1970s.
  - Sheet Music and note, 1941, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Report by Epsilon Theta Chapter, "Coedity and Sigma Nu," 1972 (Box 3)
  - The Atled, 1970s (Box 3)
  - Informational Pamphlet on Gamma Nu Chapter, 1970s (Box 3)
  - College Chapters Manual, 1977 (Box 3)